<![%workaround;[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE abstract PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
       "file:///usr/share/sgml/docbook/dtd/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
	<!ENTITY hxt  "HXT">
	<!ENTITY hxtl "Haskell XML Toolbox">
]]>

<!--
<citation><link linkend="bib_hxml">WWW13</link></citation>
is a hack for
<citation><xref linkend="bib_hxml"></citation>

xref tags produce line breaks in abstract sections
-->

<abstract>
	<title>Abstract</title>

	<para>
	This thesis introduces the core component of the Haskell XML Toolbox: a validating XML parser that supports almost fully the &xmlspecl; <citation><link linkend="bib_xml">WWW01</link></citation>. The thesis presents how a validating XML parser and XML processing applications can be implemented by using filter functions as a uniform design.
	</para>

	<para>
	The &hxtl; is a collection of tools for processing XML with Haskell. It is itself purely written in Haskell. The Toolbox is a project of the University of Applied Sciences Wedel, initialized by Prof. Dr. Uwe Schmidt.
	</para>

	<para>
	The &hxtl; bases on the ideas of HaXml <citation><link linkend="bib_haxml">WWW21</link></citation> and HXML <citation><link linkend="bib_hxml">WWW25</link></citation>, but introduces a more general approach for processing XML with Haskell. It uses a generic data model for representing XML documents, including the DTD subset and the document subset. This data model makes is possible to use filter functions as a uniform design of XML processing applications. Libraries with filters and combinators are provided for processing this data model.
	</para>

	<para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<title>The following components are included:</title>
			<listitem>
				<para><filename>hdom</filename> - Core data types and functions for processing XML with Haskell</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><filename>hparser</filename> - XML parser</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><filename>hvalidator</filename> - Modules for validating XML documents</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><filename>hxslt</filename> - Modules for XSL transformations</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</para>

	<para>
	Prof. Dr. Uwe Schmidt wrote the basic parser and core functions. His master student Christine Nickel wrote the package <filename>hxslt</filename>, his master student Martin Schmidt wrote the package <filename>hvalidator</filename> and some parts of the parser.
	</para>

	<para></para>
	<para><command>Related work</command></para>

	<para>
	Malcolm Wallace and Colin Runciman wrote HaXml <citation><link linkend="bib_haxml">WWW21</link></citation>, a collection of utilities for using Haskell and XML together. The &hxtl; is based on their idea of using filter combinators for processing XML with Haskell.
	</para>

	<para>
	Joe English wrote HXML <citation><link linkend="bib_hxml">WWW25</link></citation>, a non-validating XML parser in Haskell. His idea of validating XML by using derivatives of regular expressions <citation><link linkend="bib_derivates_je">WWW26</link></citation> was implemented in the validation functions of this software.
	</para>
</abstract>
